<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thomas Goossens</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Thomas Goossens</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Blockchain for research - curated list</title>
      <link>/blog/blockchain-for-research---curated-list/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/blockchain-for-research---curated-list/</guid>
      <description>Could blockchain :
 help science reproductibility ?
 enhance research transparency ?
 avoid publication fraud ?
 enhance datasets exchanges ?
 help to fund research projects ?
 incentivize scientists ?  Let’s find out with a few lectures !
blockchain_infography
  Blockchain ‘could help combat mistrust in scientific process’
 Dash Puts Science Research On The Blockchain Academic publishing is ripe for disruption, and Dash seeks to prove a new paradigm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open-Source Geo Data and Tools</title>
      <link>/geo-tools/open_source_geo_tools_and_data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/geo-tools/open_source_geo_tools_and_data/</guid>
      <description>Online map editors &amp;amp; data visualisation tool  https://carto.com/ https://umap.openstreetmap.fr/fr/ http://geojson.io/  Geocoding  https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/Nominatim  Basemap providers  https://openmaptiles.org http://maps.stamen.com https://www.mapbox.com/ https://openaerialmap.org/ https://www.mapillary.com/ http://maperitive.net/ https://www.maptiler.com  R packages  https://rstudio.github.io/leaflet/ https://bhaskarvk.github.io/leaflet.extras/ https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/raster/index.html https://r-spatial.github.io/sf/ https://r-spatial.github.io/lwgeom/ https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/sp/index.html https://github.com/hadley/rvest http://ropensci.github.io/RSelenium/  Belgium Specific datasets  http://geopole.org/  https://epsg.io
https://openmaptiles.org signin/?route-to=https://www.mapbox.com/studio/ /#toner/12/37.7706/-122.3782
http://colorbrewer2.org https://materialdesignicons.com/ https://fontawesome.com/
http://overpass-turbo.eu/ http://srtm.csi.cgiar.org/ https://gadm.org/ http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/web/gisco/geodata/reference-data/administrative-units-statistical-units/ https://www.gpsies.com/#10_50.2944_5.0978_hikebike https://openweathermap.org/ http://www.atlas-belgique.be/cms2/ http://inspire.ngi.be/download-free/atomfeeds/AtomFeed-CLC2012-en.xml https://github.com/tmcw/awesome-geojson</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get a high resolution DEM raster for any country with R in 2 minutes</title>
      <link>/blog/get-a-high-resolution-dem-raster-for-any-country-with-r-in-2-minutes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/get-a-high-resolution-dem-raster-for-any-country-with-r-in-2-minutes/</guid>
      <description>Today I was looking for an high resolution Digital Elevation Model for a Region of Belgium. Until now, I was using the raster::getData(&amp;quot;alt&amp;quot;, country = &amp;quot;BE&amp;quot;, mask = TRUE) which only provides a low resolution DEM (5 km).
The belgian National Geographic institute provides DEM’s at high resolution (80m and 20m). These are available from their download portal. Unfortunately I have not found yet a trick to download their data automatically (RSelenium?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boost your R productivity</title>
      <link>/blog/boost-your-r-productivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/boost-your-r-productivity/</guid>
      <description>Snippets R studio doc Pay attention to escaping characters
 .Renviron Efficient R programming book
 R project + git .RData environ git for code gitignore for R
 R dir initializer  knitr doc  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Removing large files from you git version control</title>
      <link>/blog/removing-large-files-from-you-git-version-control/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/removing-large-files-from-you-git-version-control/</guid>
      <description>While working with geodata, you might often end up downloading large raw-data files likes .shp that you will need in your data process chain.
As you don&amp;rsquo;t want to keep this static files under version control, you must tell git to ignore these files. Usually, you do it by adding a rule to your .gitignore file. But what if those files were created before there were added to the .gitignore ?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickly create your R project directory tree with pre-filled common files</title>
      <link>/blog/quickly-create-your-r-project-directory-tree-with-pre-filled-common-files/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/quickly-create-your-r-project-directory-tree-with-pre-filled-common-files/</guid>
      <description>Each time you start a new R project, it is highly recommanded to prepare a clean and organized working directory
If you regularly create new projects, this working directory preparation task might seem tedious and time consuming. Creating the folders, intializing git, creating a license file, a readme file, etc.
Instead of copying/pasting an existing pristine directory tree, I propose you to use the power of linux bash scripting.
I’ve built a little script, inspired from frdvnw, that will allow you to quickly create a new R project directory tree along with all its commonly required files.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to quickly create and maintain a blog with R ?</title>
      <link>/blog/how-to-quickly-create-and-maintain-a-blog-with-r-/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/how-to-quickly-create-and-maintain-a-blog-with-r-/</guid>
      <description>Maintaining a blog allows you to keep track of what you have done and thought. When you don’t remember how did you succeed to find a solution to a tricky problem, browsing your old posts might help you. As a scientist, it’s also the perfect tool to communicate your results to a wider audience. Moreover it allows you to showcase your work and possibly get hired for a future project. Nowadays many tools exist for you to publish on the web.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Producing and mapping gridded datasets with uncertainty using R</title>
      <link>/blog/producing-and-mapping-gridded-datasets-with-uncertainty-using-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/producing-and-mapping-gridded-datasets-with-uncertainty-using-r/</guid>
      <description>In the context of the Agromet project, we need to produce gridded maps of temperature using data acquired by a network of 30 automatic weather stations (AWS) spatially distributed in Wallonia. To each cell, an indicator of uncertainty (i.e. prediction error) must also be attached. Providing this uncertainty is of major importance because errors are not likely to be spatially homogeneous but will rather depend of the spatial arrangement of available points used to compute the model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A methodological approach to assess the best weather spatialization technique</title>
      <link>/blog/a-methodological-approach-to-assess-the-best-weather-spatialization-technique/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/a-methodological-approach-to-assess-the-best-weather-spatialization-technique/</guid>
      <description>1. Context &amp;amp; objectives 1.1. Context European directive 2009/128/CE : establishing a framework for Community action to achieve the sustainable use of pesticides
 more  The European directive 2009/128/CE imposes member-states to set up tools that allow for a more rational use of crop protection products. Among these tools, agricultural warning systems, based on crop monitoring models for the control of pests and diseases are widely adopted and have proved their efficiency.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A review of weather spatialization projects</title>
      <link>/blog/a-review-of-weather-spatialization-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/a-review-of-weather-spatialization-projects/</guid>
      <description>Introduction and context The aim of the Agromet project is to provide a near real-time hourly gridded datasets of weather parameters at the resolution of 1 km² for the whole region of Wallonia characterized by a quality indicator.
The Agromet project is largely inspired by what the ZEPP has developed in the context of their late blight warning services (see academic paper).
Before starting the development of our own service, we decided to submit a survey to our end users and to perform a preliminary benchmark of weather data interpolation facilities developed by other institutions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial interpolation using multiple linear regression : a beginners&#39;s overview (R implementation)</title>
      <link>/blog/spatial-interpolation-using-multiple-linear-regression--a-beginnerss-overview-r-implementation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/spatial-interpolation-using-multiple-linear-regression--a-beginnerss-overview-r-implementation/</guid>
      <description>The AGROMET Project lead by the Walloon agricultural research center (CRA-W) requires to generate spatialized weather dataset. In this context, multiple spatialization methods will be tested and evaluated among which the multiple regression technique. This post provides an introductory material to the multiple regression modeling technique applied to spatial data. It is not a tutorial and it is rather aimed at paving the way for beginners who want to take their first steps into in the field of applied geostatistics (with R) by defining key concepts and providing a lot of external resources worth reading !</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickly publish your R interactive data visualization tools with github pages</title>
      <link>/blog/quickly-publish-your-r-interactive-data-visualization-tools-with-github-pages/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/quickly-publish-your-r-interactive-data-visualization-tools-with-github-pages/</guid>
      <description>As a data scientist, you certainly produce a bunch of tables, plots, maps and many other kind of outputs to let your data “speak for itself”. This is your core business and I’m sure you do it pretty well ! But when it comes to make this data available to your target audience things can quickly get more frustrating. How to share these outputs in a format that everyone can open ?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using R with Docker</title>
      <link>/blog/using-r-with-docker/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/using-r-with-docker/</guid>
      <description>Why should you do that ? There are two main reasons to use R in conjunction with Docker. First, it allows you to quickly and easily share your work wathever the OS and R configuration of your collaborators. Hassle free collaboration ! Second, it allows you to work in an isolated environment. This means that you will never pollute your OS and e.g. run in time-consuming re-installation procedures due to broken configuration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessing the agreement between two quantitative methods of measurements : understanding the Bland Altman analysis</title>
      <link>/blog/assessing-the-agreement-between-two-quantitative-methods-of-measurements--understanding-the-bland-altman-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/assessing-the-agreement-between-two-quantitative-methods-of-measurements--understanding-the-bland-altman-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Attempting to statistically assess the agreement between two quantitative methods of measurements requires a validation tool.
A widely adopted tool is the correlation study computed with one method as predictor and the other as response variable (e.g. see this publication that compares temperature measurements obtained by two different kind of weather stations at the exact same location).
However, as described by Giavarina (2015), correlation study should not be used to asses the comparatibility or agreement between two instruments (because it studies the relation between one variable and the other and not the differences).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Installing Ubuntu gnome 16.04 on a windows machine</title>
      <link>/blog/installing-ubuntu-gnome-16.04-on-a-windows-machine/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/installing-ubuntu-gnome-16.04-on-a-windows-machine/</guid>
      <description>Download the .iso file Head at https://wiki.ubuntu.com/UbuntuGNOME/GetUbuntuGNOME and select the proper version (64bit)
Create a booting USB drive  If you have access to a Linux computer, launch startup disk creator
 Once launched, select the USB drive on which you want to install Linux and select the iso file you have just downloaded
 Click make Startup Disk
 Once you get notified that the installation is finished, eject the USB drive</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation of the Agromet Project</title>
      <link>/blog/presentation-of-the-agromet-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/presentation-of-the-agromet-project/</guid>
      <description>The AGROMET Project Construction of an operational web-platform designed for real-time agro-meteorological data dissemination at high spatial (1km²) and temporal (hourly) resolution.
Context The European directive 2009/128/CE imposes member-states to set up tools that allow for a more rational use of crop protection products. Among these tools, agricultural warning systems, based on crop monitoring models for the control of pests and diseases are widely adopted and have proved their efficiency. However, due to the difficulty to get meteorological data at high spatial resolution (at the parcel scale), they still are underused.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Configurer un accès SSH à un hébergement mutualisé</title>
      <link>/blog/configurer-un-acc%C3%A8s-ssh-%C3%A0-un-h%C3%A9bergement-mutualis%C3%A9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/configurer-un-acc%C3%A8s-ssh-%C3%A0-un-h%C3%A9bergement-mutualis%C3%A9/</guid>
      <description>Disposer d’un d’accès SSH vous permet de réellement avoir la main sur votre hébergement mutualisé (qui n’est rien d’autre qu’un accès limité à certains dossiers et programmes stockés sur un serveur tournant généralement sous Linux).
Grâce à votre accès SSH, vous pourrez notamment y exécuter des commandes unix et git directement depuis le terminal de votre ordinateur personnel. C’est l’outil idéal pour la maintenance de votre site WordPress par exemple !</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meta</title>
      <link>/about/colofon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/colofon/</guid>
      <description>Why this website ? A website is highly useful for yourself to keep track of what you have done and thought. Sometimes you may go back to a certain old post of yours to relearn the tricks or methods you once mastered in the past but have forgotten.
 How is it built ? This website is built with R blogdown which uses a combination of Hugo, Rmarkdown and knitr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/geo-tools/open_source_geo_tools_and_data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/geo-tools/open_source_geo_tools_and_data/</guid>
      <description>Open-Source Geo Data and Tools       code{white-space: pre;} pre:not([class]) { background-color: white; }  if (window.hljs) { hljs.configure({languages: []}); hljs.initHighlightingOnLoad(); if (document.readyState &amp;&amp; document.readyState === &#34;complete&#34;) { window.setTimeout(function() { hljs.initHighlighting(); }, 0); } }  h1 { font-size: 34px; } h1.title { font-size: 38px; } h2 { font-size: 30px; } h3 { font-size: 24px; } h4 { font-size: 18px; } h5 { font-size: 16px; } h6 { font-size: 12px; } .</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>