<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Geomatic on pokyah - opensource science, GIS and data-analysis</title>
    <link>/categories/geomatic/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Geomatic on pokyah - opensource science, GIS and data-analysis</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Jul 2018 12:52:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/geomatic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Interactively-Mapping-Spatial-Prediction-With-the-Attached-Standard-Error-Using-Mlr-Gstat-and-Leaflet</title>
      <link>/post/interactively-mapping-spatial-prediction-with-the-attached-standard-error-using-mlr-gstat-and-leaflet/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jul 2018 12:52:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/interactively-mapping-spatial-prediction-with-the-attached-standard-error-using-mlr-gstat-and-leaflet/</guid>
      <description>Here we demonstrate how to map the prediction together with the uncertainty in an intuitive and intelligible way. Our approach is based on this post by Tomislav Hengl and this post by Penn state college of earth and mineral sciences
# For the example, using the output of mlr gstat KED from previous section # loading datasets data(meuse) data(meuse.grid) # imputing values to missing data meuse = impute(meuse, classes = list(numeric = imputeMean(), factor = imputeMode()), dummy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Curated list of Open Source Geo Data and Tools</title>
      <link>/geo-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/geo-tools/</guid>
      <description>Online map editors &amp;amp; data visualisation tool  https://carto.com/ https://umap.openstreetmap.fr/fr/   Geocoding  https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/Nominatim   Basemap providers  https://openmaptiles.org http://maps.stamen.com https://www.mapbox.com/ https://openaerialmap.org/ https://www.mapillary.com/ http://maperitive.net/ https://www.maptiler.com https://openmaptiles.org   R packages  https://rstudio.github.io/leaflet/ https://bhaskarvk.github.io/leaflet.extras/ https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/raster/index.html https://r-spatial.github.io/sf/ https://r-spatial.github.io/lwgeom/ https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/sp/index.html https://github.com/hadley/rvest http://ropensci.github.io/RSelenium/   Simple Online tools  https://epsg.io http://geojson.io/   Design, fonts and icons  http://colorbrewer2.org https://materialdesignicons.com/ https://fontawesome.com/   datasets  http://geopole.org/ https://gadm.org/ http://overpass-turbo.eu/ http://srtm.csi.cgiar.org/ https://photovoltaic-software.com/solar-radiation-database.php http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/web/gisco/geodata/reference-data/administrative-units-statistical-units/ https://www.gpsies.com/#10_50.2944_5.0978_hikebike https://openweathermap.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get a high resolution DEM raster for any country with R in 2 minutes</title>
      <link>/post/srtm_data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/srtm_data/</guid>
      <description>Today I was looking for an high resolution Digital Elevation Model for a Region of Belgium. Until now, I was using the raster::getData(&amp;quot;alt&amp;quot;, country = &amp;quot;BE&amp;quot;, mask = TRUE) which only provides a low resolution DEM (5 km).
The belgian National Geographic institute provides DEM’s at high resolution (80m and 20m). These are available from their download portal. Unfortunately I have not found yet a trick to download their data automatically (RSelenium?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Producing and mapping gridded datasets with uncertainty using R</title>
      <link>/post/gridded-uncertainty/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/gridded-uncertainty/</guid>
      <description>In the context of the Agromet project, we need to produce gridded maps of temperature using data acquired by a network of 30 automatic weather stations (AWS) spatially distributed in Wallonia. To each cell, an indicator of uncertainty (i.e. prediction error) must also be attached. Providing this uncertainty is of major importance because errors are not likely to be spatially homogeneous but will rather depend of the spatial arrangement of available points used to compute the model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A review of weather spatialization projects</title>
      <link>/post/spatialization-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/spatialization-review/</guid>
      <description>Introduction and context The aim of the Agromet project is to provide a near real-time hourly gridded datasets of weather parameters at the resolution of 1 km² for the whole region of Wallonia characterized by a quality indicator.
The Agromet project is largely inspired by what the ZEPP has developed in the context of their late blight warning services (see academic paper).
Before starting the development of our own service, we decided to submit a survey to our end users and to perform a preliminary benchmark of weather data interpolation facilities developed by other institutions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial interpolation using multiple linear regression : a beginners&#39;s overview (R implementation)</title>
      <link>/post/spatial-interpolation-using-multiple-linear-regression-a-beginners-overview-r-implementation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/spatial-interpolation-using-multiple-linear-regression-a-beginners-overview-r-implementation/</guid>
      <description>The AGROMET Project lead by the Walloon agricultural research center (CRA-W) requires to generate spatialized weather dataset. In this context, multiple spatialization methods will be tested and evaluated among which the multiple regression technique. This post provides an introductory material to the multiple regression modeling technique applied to spatial data. It is not a tutorial and it is rather aimed at paving the way for beginners who want to take their first steps into in the field of applied geostatistics (with R) by defining key concepts and providing a lot of external resources worth reading !</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>