<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Productivity on pokyah - opensource science, GIS and data-analysis</title>
    <link>/tags/productivity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Productivity on pokyah - opensource science, GIS and data-analysis</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Boost your R productivity</title>
      <link>/post/how-to-boost-your-r-productivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/how-to-boost-your-r-productivity/</guid>
      <description>Dockerized R studio Serve multiple instances of R studio server (free version) at multiple ports for parallel tasks.
An extensive documentation is available on the rocker-org wiki
sudo docker run -w /home/rstudio/ --rm -p 1515:8787 -v /home/&amp;lt;hostusername&amp;gt;/:/home/rstudio/ pokyah/agrometeordocker sudo docker run -w /home/rstudio/ --rm -p 1414:8787 -v /home/&amp;lt;hostusername&amp;gt;/:/home/rstudio/ pokyah/agrometeordocker  Shiny apps as package + dockerized shiny server See doc from rocker-org shiny server Docker image and Dean Attali Stackoverflow answser regarding shinyapps as packages</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickly create your R project directory tree with pre-filled common files</title>
      <link>/post/r-project-initializer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/r-project-initializer/</guid>
      <description>Each time you start a new R project, it is highly recommanded to prepare a clean and organized working directory
If you regularly create new projects, this working directory preparation task might seem tedious and time consuming. Creating the folders, intializing git, creating a license file, a readme file, etc.
Instead of copying/pasting an existing pristine directory tree, I propose you to use the power of linux bash scripting.
I’ve built a little script, inspired from frdvnw, that will allow you to quickly create a new R project directory tree along with all its commonly required files.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>