<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Linux on pokyah - opensource science, GIS and data-analysis</title>
    <link>/categories/linux/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Linux on pokyah - opensource science, GIS and data-analysis</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/categories/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickly create your R project directory tree with pre-filled common files</title>
      <link>/post/r-project-initializer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/r-project-initializer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Each time you start a new R project, it is &lt;strong&gt;highly recommanded&lt;/strong&gt; to prepare a clean and &lt;a href=&#34;https://nicercode.github.io/blog/2013-05-17-organising-my-project/&#34;&gt;organized working directory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you regularly create new projects, this working directory preparation task might seem tedious and time consuming. Creating the folders, intializing git, creating a license file, a readme file, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of copying/pasting an existing pristine directory tree, I propose you to use the power of linux bash scripting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve built a little script, inspired from &lt;a href=&#34;https://frdvnw.github.io/data-sciences/linux/2018/04/12/my-r-skeletton.html&#34;&gt;frdvnw&lt;/a&gt;, that will allow you to quickly create a new R project directory tree along with all its commonly required files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what does the script actually do ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It pulls the Github R .gitgnore template file and make it your .gitignore file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It pulls the GNU GPL V3 license from gnu.org and make it your LICENSE file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It pulls a default init.R script from its repo. This init.R file contains a YAML header + Terms of Services footer + my habitual R script initialization functions (load common libraries, etc…)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It creates the tree structure (data folder, output folder, img fodlers, etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It intialize a new git repository and make a first commit for you ;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to give it a try, head at its &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pokyah/R-project-init&#34;&gt;repo&lt;/a&gt;, fork/clone and play it !&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using R with Docker</title>
      <link>/post/using-r-with-docker/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/using-r-with-docker/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Why should you do that ? There are two main reasons to use R in conjunction with Docker. First, it allows you to quickly and easily share your work wathever the OS and R configuration of your collaborators. Hassle free collaboration ! Second, it allows you to work in an isolated environment. This means that you will never pollute your OS and e.g. run in time-consuming re-installation procedures due to broken configuration. In case of OS crash, simply relaunch your &lt;em&gt;Docker R container&lt;/em&gt; with a single command (more about containers below) and you are ready to work !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tutorial is an introduction to R with Docker. It it not an extensive description of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.docker.com/&#34;&gt;enormous amount of features&lt;/a&gt; and all the complexity of Docker. It’s rather a good base to get started that I’ve written based on my own R development needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-is-a-docker-container&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is a Docker container ?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Docker is the piece of software that allows you to run &lt;strong&gt;containers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.docker.com/what-container&#34;&gt;official Docker website&lt;/a&gt; :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A container image is a lightweight, stand-alone, executable package of a piece of software that includes everything needed to run it: code, runtime, system tools, system libraries, settings. Available for both Linux and Windows based apps, containerized software will always run the same, regardless of the environment. Containers isolate software from its surroundings, for example differences between development and staging environments and help reduce conflicts between teams running different software on the same infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This container approach has many advantages compares to the use of virtual machines : lightweight, quick and modular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Docker terminology, a containers actually means a running instance of an &lt;strong&gt;image&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, from the official Docker Website :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Docker images are the basis of containers. An Image is an ordered collection of root filesystem changes and the corresponding execution parameters for use within a container runtime. An image typically contains a union of layered filesystems stacked on top of each other. An image does not have state and it never changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-docker-will-help-you-with-your-r-related-work&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How Docker will help you with your R related work ?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you understand what a container is, I’ll tell you what you can do with Docker in the context of you R work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can create and use a container that runs with the Linux distro &lt;em&gt;of your choice&lt;/em&gt;, with a version of R &lt;em&gt;of your choice&lt;/em&gt;, the packages and required OS dependencies &lt;em&gt;of your choices&lt;/em&gt;, and all of this in a totally isolated environment that is setup in seconds. And of course, you can create multiple containers with various R configurations depending of your needs !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that you will never run anymore in compatibility problems. It will also make your work &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-016-0021&#34;&gt;reproductible&lt;/a&gt; as you can share your containers with colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Docker also makes the use of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.github.io/packrat/&#34;&gt;Packrat&lt;/a&gt; dependency management quite obsolete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;docker-installation-instructions&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Docker installation instructions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know why you should use Docker in the context of your R work and you want to install it now ! Well, to do it, simply follow the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.docker.com/install/linux/docker-ce/ubuntu/#install-docker-ce-1&#34;&gt;installation instructions&lt;/a&gt; on the Docker official website or follow this nice &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/how-to-install-and-use-docker-on-ubuntu-16-04&#34;&gt;Digital Ocean tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we dive into the R part, you will need to understand some essential Docker concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;essential-docker-concepts-commands&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Essential Docker concepts &amp;amp; commands&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each &lt;strong&gt;image&lt;/strong&gt; has its own &lt;strong&gt;name&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;ID&lt;/strong&gt;. You can list all your available Docker images and get their name and ID using the &lt;code&gt;image&lt;/code&gt; command :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ docker images
REPOSITORY          TAG                 IMAGE ID            CREATED             SIZE
agrometeor          latest              fea4eeec5c2a        10 days ago         2.41GB&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To &lt;strong&gt;run an image as a container&lt;/strong&gt;, simply use the &lt;code&gt;run&lt;/code&gt; command with the image ID or name :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ docker run &amp;lt;IMAGE-NAME&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that this command can receive many optional parameters (we will see an example later).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also run a container from an image which is hosted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://hub.docker.com/r/pokyah/agrometeordocker/&#34;&gt;Docker Hub&lt;/a&gt;. Docker will automatically download it on your computer and run it as a container once it is downloaded (to use this feature, you will first need to create a Docker hub account).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For geospatial R work you could for example run the image named &lt;a href=&#34;https://hub.docker.com/r/rocker/geospatial/&#34;&gt;rocker/geospatial&lt;/a&gt; which contains Linux, R, Rstudio and the most famous R spatial packages and their OS dependencies :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ docker run rocker/geospatial&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can of course run multiple different images simultanesously but you can also run a single image simultaneously in multiple separate containers. To &lt;strong&gt;list all your running Docker containers&lt;/strong&gt; and get their name and ID, use the &lt;code&gt;ps&lt;/code&gt; command. Note that the name is randomly generated by Docker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ docker ps
CONTAINER ID        IMAGE               COMMAND             CREATED             STATUS              PORTS                    NAMES
b18f77625a00        agrometeor          &amp;quot;/init&amp;quot;             About an hour ago   Up About an hour    0.0.0.0:8787-&amp;gt;8787/tcp   silly_roentgen
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running containers use computing ressources. To &lt;strong&gt;stop and remove&lt;/strong&gt; a running container use the &lt;code&gt;rm&lt;/code&gt; command :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ docker rm -f &amp;lt;CONTAINER-ID&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pay attention that when you stop a container, all the work that has been done inside the container is lost ! This is on purpose and we will later see the proper and efficient way to save your R developments made inside a container. If you want to save modifications made inside a container (e.g. adding a R library and its OS dependencies) you have to &lt;code&gt;commit&lt;/code&gt; your container. But this is out of the scope of this tutorial. If you are interested, you can read the corresponding &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/commandline/commit/#commit-a-container-with-new-configurations&#34;&gt;doc&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need it, you can explore the file system of the running container (similarly to what you do when you are connected to a server using ssh conection) :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ docker exec -t -i &amp;lt;CONTAINER-ID&amp;gt; /bin/bash&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Docker is not limited to images existing on Docker Hub. It allows you to create your images with the configuration of your own. Creativity is the limit. Creating a Docker image requires a &lt;strong&gt;Dockfile&lt;/strong&gt; which is simply a configuration file that tells Docker what to put in your image. For example, you can find the Dockfile that was used to create the rocker/geospatial image that we mentioned earlier on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rocker-org/geospatial/blob/master/Dockerfile&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; . To &lt;strong&gt;build an image&lt;/strong&gt; from a dockfile you simply open a terminal in the folder containing the dockfile and execute the &lt;code&gt;build&lt;/code&gt; command with the name you want to attribute to your image (don’t forget the “.” at the end !) :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ docker build -t &amp;lt;IMAGE-NAME&amp;gt; .&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There a lot of ressources on the web that explain how to create your own images. Check my selection in the further reading section at the end of the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you are sure you will not anymore run an image as container(s), you can delete it to save some space on your computer :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ docker rmi &amp;lt;IMAGE_NAME:VERSION/IMAGE-ID&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And to delete all images (really ?!) :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ docker rmi $(docker images -qf &amp;quot;dangling=true&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;using-rstudio-inside-a-docker-container-and-saving-your-work&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Using RStudio inside a Docker container and saving your work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s dive in the latest part of this tutorial : running R inside a container. It’s actually pretty simple. It involves 2 steps :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choosing the pre-build R oriented Docker image you want to use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running it as a container with optional parameters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you need to make some R developments made easier with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tidyverse.org/&#34;&gt;tidyverse&lt;/a&gt; family packages. To do this you will download the pre-built &lt;a href=&#34;https://hub.docker.com/r/rocker/tidyverse/image&#34;&gt;rocker/tidyverse&lt;/a&gt; from Docker hub using the command &lt;code&gt;pull&lt;/code&gt; (note the similarity with &lt;a href=&#34;http://r-bio.github.io/intro-git-rstudio/&#34;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ docker pull rocker/tidyverse&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that we have learned that once closed, containers loose all the modifications you have made within it. So, &lt;strong&gt;how to save your R developments made within a container&lt;/strong&gt; ? The trick is to actually &lt;strong&gt;mount your project folder from your host computer to the container&lt;/strong&gt;. This is achieved by passing optional parameters to the &lt;code&gt;run&lt;/code&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to run a container from the rocker/tidyverse image with an R project located in your host computer at &lt;code&gt;/home/yourUsername/Rprojects/yourProject/&lt;/code&gt; and work in RStudio, use the &lt;code&gt;run&lt;/code&gt; command with these optional parameters :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ docker run -w /home/rstudio/ rm -p 8787:8787 -v /yourUsername/Rprojects/yourProject/:/home/rstudio/ rocker/tidyverse&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Docker will instantiate a new container from the rocker/tidyverse image and make your project folder available to the container by mounting it. All the modifications that you made to your mounted host folder from your container will be effective in your host machine. So once you stop your container, don’t worry, your modifications will be saved !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To launch your container RStudio install, open a web-browser and navigate to &lt;code&gt;http://localhost:8787&lt;/code&gt;. You habitual RStudio interface will be launched within a few seconds and your mounted folder will appear in the files pane. &lt;strong&gt;Congratulations, you are now ready to work within a dockerized RStudio install !&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In most of the cases, before running an image, you will need to customise it so that it reflects your own needs. &lt;strong&gt;Customising an image&lt;/strong&gt; requires to &lt;strong&gt;edit its Dockerfile&lt;/strong&gt; and rebuild the image as mentioned earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To keep &lt;strong&gt;git versioned Dockerfile -s&lt;/strong&gt; of your images, you can push them to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;. Hosting your Dockerfile on Github offers you a nice feature : &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.docker.com/docker-hub/builds/&#34;&gt;automated builds&lt;/a&gt;. Once enabled, each time you push a modification of your Dockerfile to Github, Docker will rebuild your image and make it ready to be pulled by others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can share this very specific R environment with your co-workers. First, share them this tutorial and then share your image. For this purpose, you have two solutions :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sending them the corresponding Dockerfile and let them build the image on their machine (more complex)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upload your image to Docker hub (manually or with the automated build feature) and simply send them the name of your image so that then can you it immediately use it with the &lt;code&gt;run&lt;/code&gt; command&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;conclusion&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have learned how to use Docker to run your own customized R isolated environment inside a container and how to share this specific environment with your colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to try a my pokyah/agrometeor container, have a look at its &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pokyah/agrometeorDocker&#34;&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt;. There you will also learn how to create a custom bash command to launch your containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a next tutorial, I’ll explain you how to run a container able to connect to an external postgreSQL database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;future-readings&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Future readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;good-tutorials&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Good tutorials&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.andrewheiss.com/blog/2017/04/27/super-basic-practical-guide-to-docker-and-rstudio/&#34;&gt;Andrew Heiss tuto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dirk.eddelbuettel.com/papers/useR2015_docker.pdf&#34;&gt;Dirk Eddelbuettel presentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://knausb.github.io/2017/06/running-r-in-docker/&#34;&gt;Brian J. Knaus CLI tuto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.r-bloggers.com/r-3-3-0-is-another-motivation-for-docker/&#34;&gt;R-Blogger post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;dockerfile-customization&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dockerfile customization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://o2r.info/2017/05/30/containerit-package/&#34;&gt;R package to create Dockerfile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ropenscilabs.github.io/r-docker-tutorial/05-dockerfiles.html&#34;&gt;tutorial from ropenscilabs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mirantis.com/blog/how-do-i-create-a-new-docker-image-for-my-application/&#34;&gt;mirantis blog tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/45289764/install-r-packages-using-docker-file&#34;&gt;stackoverflow install-r-packages-using-docker-file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/46902203/verify-r-packages-installed-into-docker-container&#34;&gt;stackoverflow verify-r-packages-installed-into-docker-container&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/26500174/upload-local-files-to-docker-container?noredirect=1&amp;amp;lq=1&#34;&gt;stackoverflow upload-local-files-to-docker-container&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Configurer un accès SSH à un hébergement mutualisé</title>
      <link>/post/configurer-un-acces-ssh-a-un-hebergement-mutualise/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/configurer-un-acces-ssh-a-un-hebergement-mutualise/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Disposer d’un d’accès &lt;a href=&#34;https://code.tutsplus.com/tutorials/ssh-what-and-how--net-25138&#34;&gt;SSH&lt;/a&gt; vous permet de réellement avoir la main sur votre hébergement mutualisé (qui n’est rien d’autre qu’un accès limité à certains dossiers et programmes stockés sur un serveur tournant généralement sous Linux).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grâce à votre accès SSH, vous pourrez notamment y exécuter des commandes &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tutorialspoint.com/unix/&#34;&gt;unix&lt;/a&gt; et &lt;a href=&#34;https://confluence.atlassian.com/bitbucketserver/basic-git-commands-776639767.html&#34;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; directement depuis le terminal de votre ordinateur personnel. C’est l’outil idéal pour la maintenance de votre site WordPress par exemple !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Avant de vous lancer dans la configuration de votre accès SSH, vérifiez d’abord que votre hébergeur offre cette possibilité. Ce tutoriel a été élaboré via un hébergement &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.infomaniak.com/&#34;&gt;Infomaniak&lt;/a&gt; mais rien ne devrait être fort différent si vous êtes chez un autre hébergeur offrant cette possibilité.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ce tutoriel est uniquement valable pour les utilisateurs Linux et Mac. Pour ce qui est de Windows, référez-vous à un autre tutoriel (faites une recherche sur “putty”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;etape-1-creez-un-compte-dacces-ftpssh-a-votre-espace-mutualise.&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Etape 1 : Créez un compte d’accès FTP/SSH à votre espace mutualisé.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Via l’interface d’administration de votre hébergeur, créez un compte d’accès FTP/SSH avec mot de passe. Pour Infomaniak, tout est expliqué &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.infomaniak.com/fr/support/faq/1982/creermodifiersupprimer-un-compte-ftp-gerer-les-comptesacces-ftp&#34;&gt;ici&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;etape-2-creez-une-clef-ssh-sur-votre-ordinateur-personnel.&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Etape 2 : Créez une clef SSH sur votre ordinateur personnel.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sur votre ordinateur, ouvrez le terminal (shell) et lancez la commande de création d’une clef SSH :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;myUserName:~$ ssh-keygen -t dsa&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le shell vous demandera dans quel répertoire vous souhaitez enregistrer votre clef. Appuyez simplement sur enter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Generating public /private dsa key pair. Enter file in which to save the 
key (/home/clients/randomStringOfNumbersAndLetters/.ssh/id_dsa): Enter 
passphrase (empty for no passphrase):&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;L’invite de commande vous demandera ensuite de créer un mot de passe. Pensez à un mot de passe facile à taper car vous serez souvent invités à l’entrer :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Enter passphrase (empty for no passphrase):&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le shell vous précisera alors quelle est l’empreinte de votre clef et son &lt;em&gt;randomart&lt;/em&gt;. La définition de ces termes barbares sort un peu du contexte de ce tutoriel. Je vous invite à vous documenter par vous-même si vous souhaitez en apprendre un peu plus sur les différentes subtilités sous-jacentes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Your identification has been saved in 
/home/clients/myClientIDNumber/.ssh/id_dsa.
Your public key has been saved in 
/home/clients/myClientIDNumber/.ssh/id_dsa.pub. The key fingerprint is: 
xx:xx:xx:xx:xx:xx:xx:xx:xx:xx:xx:xx:xx:xx:xx:xx uid68541@h2web77 The 
key&amp;#39;s randomart image is: +--[ DSA 1024]----+ | | | | | | | | | | | | | 
| | | | | +-----------------+&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Récupérez la chaine de caractère correspondant à votre clef publique :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;myUserName:~$ cat /Users/myUserName/.ssh/id_rsa.pub&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copiez la clef publique que vous fournit le shell. Exemple de clef fournie :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssh -dss 
AAAAB3NzaC1yc2EAAAABIwAAAQEAklOUpkDHrfHY17SbrmTIpNLTGK9Tjom/BWDSUGPl+nafzlHDTYW7hdI4yZ5ew18JH4JW9jbhUFrviQzM7xlELEVf4h9lFX5QVkbPppSwg0cda3Pbv7kOdJ/MTyBlWXFCR+HAo3FXRitBqxiX1nKhXpHAZsMciLq8V6RjsNAQwdsdMFvSlVK/7XAt3FaoJoAsncM1Q9x5+3V0Ww68``/eIFmb1zuUFljQJKprrX88XypNDvjYNby6vw/Pb0rwert/EnmZ+AW4OZPnTPI89ZPmVMLuayrD2cE86Z/il8b+gw3r3+1nKatmIkjn2so1d01QraTlMqVSsbxNrRFi9wrf+M7Q== myUserName@mycomputer.local&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ouvrez un éditeur de texte (Vim, Nano, Emacs, Atom, gedit, etc), collez-y la clef et enregistrez le fichier sous le nom &lt;em&gt;authorized_keys&lt;/em&gt; (sans extension).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;etape-3-creez-sur-lhebergement-mutualise-le-repertoire-dans-lequel-enregistrer-les-clefs-ssh-autorisees&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Etape 3 : Créez, sur l’hébergement mutualisé, le répertoire dans lequel enregistrer les clefs SSH autorisées&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A la racine de votre répertoire, créez un dossier .ssh dans lequel vous uploadez en FTP ou via l’interface en ligne de gestions de fichiers, le fichier &lt;em&gt;authorized_keys&lt;/em&gt; fraichement créé sur votre ordinateur personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;etape-4-testez-votre-connexion-ssh&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Etape 4 : Testez votre connexion SSH&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ca y est, votre ordinateur est maintenant autorisé à accéder en SSH à votre espace partagé. Afin de vous connecter, entrez la commande suivante :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;myComputerName:~ myUserName$ ssh hostFTPSSHlogin@hostServer&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remplacez &lt;code&gt;_hostFTPSSHlogin_&lt;/code&gt; et &lt;code&gt;_hostServer_&lt;/code&gt; par les infos qui vous sont fournis par votre hébergeur. Chez infomaniak, vous trouverez ces informations dans votre panneau d’administration à la rubrique :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Accueil/Domaine &amp;amp; Hébergement/Gestion De sHébergements/mon Nom de Domaine/Comptes FT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vous serez ensuite invités à entrer votre mot de passe de connection FTP/SSH créé à l’étape 1 :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;hostFTPSSHlogin@hostServerName&amp;#39;s password:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entrez-le, validez en appuyant sur enter et si tout ce passe bien, vous devriez maintenant être connecté en SSH à votre hébergement mutualisé. Un moyen rapide de voir si votre connection est bien effective, est que votre invite de commande ne commence plus par&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;myComputerName:~ myUserName$&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;mais plutôt par quelque chose ressemblant à ce ceci :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;userName@hostName: /home/clients/randomStringOfNumbersAndLetters $&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Si c’est le cas, &lt;strong&gt;félicitations&lt;/strong&gt; ! Vous disposez maintenant d’un accès SSH à votre espace mutualisé. Grâce à cet accès, vous serez par exemple en mesure de &lt;em&gt;puller&lt;/em&gt; les derniers &lt;em&gt;commits&lt;/em&gt; du développement de votre site web hébergés en privé sur Bitbucket. Dans un prochain post, nous verrons d’ailleurs comment configurer un workflow de mise en production et mise à jour de votre site web à l’aide de git et SSH.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;etape-5-changez-les-permissions-du-dossier-.ssh-et-du-fichier-authorized_keys&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Etape 5 : Changez les permissions du dossier .ssh et du fichier &lt;em&gt;authorized_keys&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pour des raisons de sécurité, réglez les &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thinkplexx.com/learn/article/unix/command/chmod-permissions-flags-explained-600-0600-700-777-100-etc&#34;&gt;permissions&lt;/a&gt; de votre dossier .ssh à 700 et celles du fichier _authorized_keys _à 600. Ces recommandations proviennent d’&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.infomaniak.com/en/support/faq/2054/logging-into-your-hosting-with-an-ssh-key&#34;&gt;Infomaniak&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commencez par vous rendre à la racine de votre hébergement mutualisé&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;userName@hostName: /home/clients/randomStringOfNumbersAndLetters $ 
cd ~/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Réglez la permission de votre répertoire .ssh à 700&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;userName@hostName:~/$ chmod 700 .ssh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allez dans le répertoire .ssh contenant le fichier &lt;strong&gt;authorized_keys&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;userName@hostName:~/$ cd .ssh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Réglez la permission de votre fichier authorized_keys à 600&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;userName@hostName:~/.ssh $ chmod 600 authorized_keys&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;etape-6-en-option-changez-le-mot-de-passe-de-votre-clef-ssh&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Etape 6 (en option) : Changez le mot de passe de votre clef SSH&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Si à l’usage, vous vous rendez compte que votre mot de passe est trop fastidieux à entrer, vous pouvez le changer voire le supprimer (non recommandé). Pour ce, lorsque vous êtes connectés en SSH à votre espace mutualisé (voir étape 4) , entrez la commande suivante :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;userName@hostName:/home/clients/randomStringOfNumbersAndLetters $ 
ssh -keygen -p&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vous serez alors invités à entrer le chemin de destination de votre clef :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Enter file in which the key is 
(/home/clients/randomStringOfNumbersAndLetters/.ssh/id_rsa):&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entrez le chemin suivant :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;/home/clients/randomStringOfNumbersAndLetters/.ssh/id_dsa&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vous serez invités à taper l’ancien mot de passe :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Enter old passphrase:
Key has comment` 
&amp;#39;/home/clients/randomStringOfNumbersAndLetters/.ssh/id_dsa&amp;#39;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entrez-le et validez en tapant enter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;L’invite de commande vous demandera alors d’entrer un nouveau mot de passe :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Enter new passphrase (empty for no passphrase):&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choisissez votre nouveau mot de passe ou taper simplement enter pour désactiver l’utilisation d’un mot de passe (non recommandé).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Si le fait de devoir entrez un mot de passe trop souvent vous ennuie, vous pouvez &lt;a href=&#34;https://unix.stackexchange.com/questions/12195/how-to-avoid-being-asked-passphrase-each-time-i-push-to-bitbucket&#34;&gt;créer un &lt;strong&gt;agent&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; qui le retiendra pour vous lors de la session active.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>