<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Weather on pokyah - opensource science, GIS and data-analysis</title>
    <link>/categories/weather/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Weather on pokyah - opensource science, GIS and data-analysis</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/weather/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A methodological approach to assess the best weather spatialization technique</title>
      <link>/post/methodological-approach-to-assess-the-best-spatial-interpolation-method/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/methodological-approach-to-assess-the-best-spatial-interpolation-method/</guid>
      <description>1. Context &amp;amp; objectives 1.1. Context European directive 2009/128/CE : establishing a framework for Community action to achieve the sustainable use of pesticides
 more  The European directive 2009/128/CE imposes member-states to set up tools that allow for a more rational use of crop protection products. Among these tools, agricultural warning systems, based on crop monitoring models for the control of pests and diseases are widely adopted and have proved their efficiency.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial interpolation using multiple linear regression : a beginners&#39;s overview (R implementation)</title>
      <link>/post/spatial-interpolation-using-multiple-linear-regression-a-beginners-overview-r-implementation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/spatial-interpolation-using-multiple-linear-regression-a-beginners-overview-r-implementation/</guid>
      <description>The AGROMET Project lead by the Walloon agricultural research center (CRA-W) requires to generate spatialized weather dataset. In this context, multiple spatialization methods will be tested and evaluated among which the multiple regression technique. This post provides an introductory material to the multiple regression modeling technique applied to spatial data. It is not a tutorial and it is rather aimed at paving the way for beginners who want to take their first steps into in the field of applied geostatistics (with R) by defining key concepts and providing a lot of external resources worth reading !</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation of the Agromet Project</title>
      <link>/post/presentation-of-agromet-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/presentation-of-agromet-project/</guid>
      <description>The AGROMET Project Construction of an operational web-platform designed for real-time agro-meteorological data dissemination at high spatial (1km²) and temporal (hourly) resolution.
Context The European directive 2009/128/CE imposes member-states to set up tools that allow for a more rational use of crop protection products. Among these tools, agricultural warning systems, based on crop monitoring models for the control of pests and diseases are widely adopted and have proved their efficiency. However, due to the difficulty to get meteorological data at high spatial resolution (at the parcel scale), they still are underused.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>